[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is nigel poulton
nigel is a docker captain and trainer of
many businesses all around the world
he is the author of two fantastic books
titled the kubernetes book
and docker deep dive he's a regular
speaker and workshop leader at leading
tech conferences
and events such as dockercon and kubecon
and many others
nigel welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything i missed in your
bio that you'd like to add
well thanks for having me and no i think
that sounded alright i'm easy
okay excellent so i've broken the show
up into
three parts so quite a immediate
introduction to lay the foundation for
the next two parts we'll move on to
kubernetes technology
and then we'll uh try to discuss
deploying an application on kubernetes
so i'd like to start with an overview of
what kubernetes
is and its history for a deeper
understanding of its history
i recommend the listeners to listen to
show 246
which was john wilkes on the borg
and kubernetes back in 2016.
so nigel what is kubernetes
so elevator pitch it is an orchestrator
of microservices applications and don't
we just love a buzzword in the industry
an orchestrator of microservices
applications let me just
try and boil that down briefly and look
we can go into more detail if you want
but
i think the modern way of developing
applications is different to what it was
certainly 10 years ago
so we're building these applications
that are built of like lots of small
specialized parts that talk to each
other via apis
and in the modern business world we want
those applications to be able to
scale up and down based on demand we
want them to be able to self
heal we want to be able to push like
rolling updates and things to them
kind of during the business day without
having to wait for long weekends and do
loads of planning for like i don't know
maybe one update a year
so you know small moving parts in our
applications
scale up scale down self-heal push
updates all the time
and we need something to sort of without
using a buzzword but
to orchestrate it or to oversee or
manage that and and that's
effectively what kubernetes does okay
is it new it feels new but it isn't
really so we've had it since i think the
summer of 2014 and i've been using it
ever since then
it is a big project or a big platform or
tool
i think the core parts of it like the
core objects that
are required to build and deploy
applications on kubernetes
they're really nicely baked and
generally available and stable and all
of that goodness
but of course then you're going to get
more
not edge case but sort of newer features
in the platform and things that are
trying to push the boundaries that are
that are a bit newer
so i think like the core components of
kubernetes
are nicely baked and are all generally
available but of course if you want to
go to the bleeding edge with some of the
newer features then
so parts of it in you without waffling
and
parts of it uh super trustworthy and
reliable i mean people are deploying
applications to kubernetes in production
left right and center these days so
it's obviously it's stable enough for a
lot of people and it's
mature enough i'm always careful when i
say you know something is enterprise
ready or
is mature gavin because terms like that
mature and enterprise ready mean
different things to different people and
different organizations
and so of course you always have to do
your own research in your own testing
but look people are using it in anger
and loving it and hating it at the same
time thanks nigel i think he touched
on this answer in my first question but
what problem does it solve so let me
give you an
analogy here and this is something that
i've given trainings and things that i
do all the time right
let me compare a modern micro services
application to a football team it can be
american football or soccer it doesn't
really matter okay
but that team is made up of lots of
individuals
and each individual has a different role
to play so in soccer
you know somebody is a goalkeeper and
other people are strikers and other
people are defenders whether it's
american football
you know there's somebody whose job is
just a kick and then you've got a
quarterback and wide receivers and
all these different things but they have
to come together to work as a team
and a micro services application is very
similar so it might have like a web
front end on it and a data store on the
back end and
some authentication and some middleware
and on their own
those elements uh they're kind of great
a little bit like a goalkeeper in in
football or soccer is great
but on their own they're not going to
accomplish very much in a game
so the individuals of a team have to
come together with a plan
and play as a team well in a micro
services application you've got all
these different moving parts
that need to come together to give an
overall useful application experience to
an end user
now in the football or soccer analogy
you have a coach comes along
and organizes everybody into positions
and arranges the tactics
if somebody gets hurt or injured they
swap them out with somebody else
if the score you know if you're down
towards the end of the game and you need
to press forward more attack more
you'll change the tactics you'll change
the personnel on the pitch
kubernetes is very similar for a
microservices application
yes all those pieces have to talk to
each other but they also have to be able
to respond to business demand
so if it's if it's whatever if it's
black friday or something right and
you're increasing demand on your system
well kubernetes can ratchet things up
so that you have more instances of your
web server and your back end to cope
with demand and then later on
in the month when things cool down it
can cool the application down
and remove instances and things like
that but also then if things break
kubernetes does what the coach on the
soccer or football team does is it takes
the broken part of the application out
of play
and replaces it with a new part and
keeps things ticking over
so basically modern microservices
applications
have to be able to respond to business
needs have to be able to self-heal all
of that stuff
kubernetes does that and if you knew
anything about
vm sprawl in like a vmware world or like
a virtualization world
you get the same with containerized
applications or microservices
applications you get
huge sprawl and you need tools to be
able to help you manage that and
kubernetes does all of that as well
why is this a hard problem and why is
kubernetes a better solution
to something in an earlier generation of
something trying to address that problem
that hard problem so i'll tell you the
reason that it's hard
back in the day we would tend to deploy
an application as a more
monolithic application and excuse me if
i'm being a bit high level
and i'm not going into detail here but
let's just call it a traditional
monolithic application you would have
everything that that application did
like the front end the authentication
the logging the database
remember i'm being super high level here
okay but it would ship as a single
binary or as a single installer
meaning that you know if you ever had to
perform an update on let's say the
reporting aspect of it
quite often you'd have to take the whole
thing down over a long weekend high risk
everyone in the office
pizzas and coffee all weekend and it was
kind of painful so we moved to this more
micro services
model where we say we take all those
different features of the application
and we break them out into their own
pieces so that we can have different
development teams working on them
we can update the reporting system
without having to touch
the web front end or the database or
whatever and it's a much better model
it allows us to scale one element
without scaling another part update one
element without updating another part
but because they're all talking via apis
over a network now
it suddenly becomes more complex so you
get a lot more
capabilities from your modern
applications they're much better suited
to modern business needs and
requirements
but gluing it all together is way harder
keeping everything talking is way harder
when you do that at
scale you can't have a human being doing
it you need a system to do it
and that system is kubernetes now to the
second part of your question and i'm
not sure whether i'm necessarily
answering your question here but
there were alternatives so docker swarm
and apache mesos
things like that can do very similar
things to kubernetes
and still do but the reason that
kubernetes grabs all of the airtime
it seems is that it has so much momentum
and so much
almost universal backing from all of the
cloud providers
from all of the enterprise data
management companies your cisco's your
hpes your
netapps people like that everybody is
behind kubernetes
so there are alternatives out there and
i'm not here to say that
you know one is better than the other
but kubernetes is looking like the
safest bet like if you're
a business and you're like we want to do
this
and we have to pick the right
technologies kubernetes is a pretty
nailed unsafe bet
we know it's going to be here in the
future and we know it's developing and
it's got a great ecosystem
because everybody is on board with it i
hope that kind of answered the question
yeah perfect i think that has probably
answers my next three
which is why is it winning and what is a
driving adoption
and how rapidly it is being adopted
yeah i think that's just because like
you said
everyone well with my business hat on
you get a bit tired trying to assess
everything out there
you know and you get to a certain point
it's like well what's everyone using you
know what big names take the boxes
would you agree with that that's what's
driving adoption is just everybody's
talking about it or
yeah i think that is certainly a big
part of it for sure
i think if we just wind the clock back a
little bit though to give some
sort of at least from my opinion and
i've been in the ecosystem industry
you know containers and stuff for a
while now what do you think is
driving adoption then for yeah so if you
think back to when amazon web services
was
new it came in from the left field and
it started eating the lunch
of your microsoft's and your ibm's and
your red hats and
your hp's and people like that and they
didn't like that and they needed an
answer to amazon web services now
i think at first it's fair to say that
we all thought that or hope that was
going to be
openstack and openstack tried very much
to be like an open source version of aws
that would go toe-to-toe feature to
feature
but be something that you didn't have to
be tied into a cloud provider for
and we did a lot of hard work around
openstack and unfortunately
no disrespect intended here at all but
it didn't end up becoming what i think a
lot of us hoped it would be
and when i say us i mean like you know a
lot of those traditional hps and cisco's
and
and microsoft and people really needed
something to compete with netapp
but openstack didn't become that again
in from the left field
and refer back to the episode that you
had in the past on borg and what have
you borg and omega probably
google launched kubernetes into the
market now
we'll hear people will say that
kubernetes is the operating system of
the cloud
and this for me is at the at the crux of
why it's
gaining so much popularity right when i
say it's the operating system in the
cloud if you think about linux or
windows being the operating system that
sits on top of
dell servers and hp servers and cisco
servers and super micro servers yeah
and one of the job of the operating
system is to abstract what that hardware
is below
so that the user of an application
doesn't have to care or even know
whether the application is running on a
dell versus a compaxer or an hpe server
yeah like why would they want to care
they don't and as long as your
application will run on linux or windows
you can move that application to a
different server hardware infrastructure
as long as you're running linux on
windows well kubernetes does the same
thing it says
we'll take your cloud infrastructure aws
google cloud platform azure all of the
others right
or even virtual machines or physicals on
premises
we'll take all of that you slap
kubernetes on top of it
and as long as your application will run
on kubernetes
the consumer of the application doesn't
have to care whether it's aws at the
bottom or you're on premises
virtual machines right and by the same
token you can take your application that
runs on kubernetes
and run it on kubernetes somewhere else
so it does that abstraction
that lets you run your code anywhere and
potentially and look it's not a silver
bullet here but it does make life easier
when it comes to things like migrations
as well so as an end user it's got a lot
of things that are advantageous
but also the ecosystem needed something
that was going to abstract
amazon web services and kubernetes
potentially does that and does it for a
lot of people so that
almost that aws or or azure or gcp or
ibm cloud or lenovo or wherever right
it's abstracted and it makes it easy for
you to pick one cloud today
realize that you made a mistake next
month and you want a different cloud
and move to it much easier than you
could if you didn't have kubernetes
now look mate i have a habit of waffling
you know i speak for a living
so i'm going to cut myself short there
and by all means tell me if that didn't
make sense
no that's good i've just got a few bits
left in the intro to sort of smooth that
off but yeah that was a great answer
thanks nigel
just some nitty-gritty what's kubernetes
written in oh yeah okay so predominantly
it's written in go
okay go along yeah what does it actually
run on
so kubernetes itself is an application
written in go
yeah so it will run on linux or windows
on anything underneath cloud instances
virtual machines and your data center
physical machines in your data center as
long as you have
linux or windows now for the most part
it's been linux but there's
catch-up being played by windows as well
so
you could have like an infinite mirror
where
you've got kubernetes running on
kubernetes running on kubernetes
running on virtual machines running on
you might not want to do that
you probably can't so what i would say
is like if you want to build it yourself
so you have a bunch of hardware in your
data center let's just take an
on-premises example but it copy cloud
instances
you slap linux on that let's say and
let's say you've got six machines
and then on those six machines you
deploy kubernetes and you would probably
without us getting into too much detail
here
deploy three manager nodes that's your
control plane that manages how the whole
cluster works
and then three worker nodes where you
run your user applications
but it's hardware be that physical tin
in your data center or cloud instances
or virtual machines because of course
they emulate hardware
you install an operating system linux or
windows and then you go to work
installing kubernetes on top of that
kubernetes forms a cluster or a
substrate or whatever
that you then deploy your applications
to excellent
so would a safe bet be some type of
virtual machine platform
which kubernetes runs on top or yeah all
the time
absolutely okay so you're still in the
virtual machine world for some
for sure for those types of things so
where can we find it
how do we get our hands on kubernetes so
lots of ways and it's got a lot simpler
these days
so let me run you through maybe two or
three scenarios so let's say you are
a developer or just somebody who wants
to play around with it on your laptop
hit google and search for either mini
cube or docker desktop
personally and it's just me they're both
great don't get me wrong personally i
prefer docker desktop
because it's click click click gui two
minutes later you've got a
you've got kubernetes up and running on
your laptop a single node cluster so
don't get me wrong it's not for
production but you get to play around on
your laptop just google docker desktop
download it mac
os and windows 10 two minutes later
you'll be in business
if you want to deploy it to the cloud
and you're relatively new the easiest
way is a hosted kubernetes service
basically that's where your trusted
cloud provider and all the big cloud
provider
in fact just about every cloud provider
has hosted kubernetes
you go there and you say i want a
kubernetes cluster with
three manager nodes for high
availability and let's say five worker
nodes to run my applications
build the working out of this number of
calls and this amount of ram
let's have this version of kubernetes
and then you click the build button
pretty much two minutes later you will
have a kubernetes cluster that you can
deploy applications to
and your cloud provider hides all of the
hard parts of
how do you make that control plane
highly available and high performance
and
how do you manage upgrades of the
control plane
hosted kubernetes your cloud provider
does all of that for you
so an easy on-ramp and then the third
way would be to build it yourself either
in the cloud or in your own data center
and that's what we talked about before
you build your infrastructure that can
be physical machines virtual machines or
cloud instances
lash an operating system on top go and
install kubernetes
sounds good yeah i've had a play with
mini cube
early last year sometime and then i'd
uninstalled it because it just sat with
a high cpu
in my machine doing nothing but that's
probably me i'll add
some show notes for the docker desktop
and what would be a good distro to use
in the linux world to run it on
i try and shy away from recommending
different products okay
it's different for different companies i
tend to go with vanilla upstream
kubernetes as much as possible
but red hat has open shift that there
are others out there as well
and i'm i'm personally quite a fan of
rancher
if you look up rancher i mean they do
great things with cooper
yeah they had a ranch at os didn't they
that's kind of end of life now i think
yes right yeah okay that's perfect well
i'll just
scoot us on to the middle section after
this last question
so given all the greatness of kubernetes
what shouldn't we use it for
all right yeah that's a really good
question so
kubernetes is definitely not for
everybody i think going forward by the
way it
will be the right choice for more and
more people
but if you're a small shop with just
a small handful of applications
kubernetes is very much potentially
overkill it has a learning curve and
you have to be able to keep up with the
updates and things like that
and in no way should your infrastructure
and i'm referring to kubernetes here as
infrastructure right
demand more of your time than your
applications if that's the case then
it's
it's probably a big sign that it's not
the right choice for you so if you are
deploying
something smaller and you're a smaller
team and you're just testing the water
with this
i highly recommend docker swarm it does
pretty much what kubernetes does but
it's way easier to install
and way easier to wrap your head around
but
the chances are that you will either
outgrow that in the future
if you grow in your business or as you
want to do
more advanced things like what docker
swarm
gains in the simplicity and the ease of
deployment category it loses in the
extensibility category
so to get started and then if you think
yes microservices applications are for
me
and we're going to deploy more and more
in anger going forward then you might
want to say well let's start moving to
kubernetes
yeah that's where we're at in my
business we're on docker swarm for the
past
two or three years so looking at all
this stuff
and it's a great product yeah i mean you
just set it and off you go when it
connects great with all the source code
repositories on their ci cd tools
i just love it but like you just said
you get to a point where you want to do
sort of half and half upgrades and you
know stuff like that
so there's a little bit of logic we have
to check if things are working before
the next step gets rolled out and things
and i think
kubernetes just does that much nicer so
we're going to move into
kubernetes terminology we've covered its
history
if listeners want to dig in a bit more
we've done a whole show on its history
a nice high level level overview view
there nigel thanks
so i'd like to discuss the terminology
we should use
what we should have in our heads when
we're thinking about the example app
we're going to talk about in the last
section
which we're going to deploy on
kubernetes so
i've got around 10 questions to sentence
a section so don't worry if we
mix and match but what are the main
components of kubernetes
so i would say like about 100 000
feet so kubernetes is a cluster that you
deploy applications to and that cluster
is made
of masters and workers the masters
you're generally speaking shouldn't be
deploying user applications to them you
should be reserving those
to basically oversee the cluster and
oversee your applications
and quite often i will refer to the
masters as the brains of the cluster
so this is where all the mod like the
scheduler runs there
the data store runs there that holds the
state of the cluster and the state of
your applications
it makes all the decisions as to which
of the worker nodes to deploy
application instances to it's where all
the logic
sits to do the scaling and the
self-healing and all the updates and
things like that
then you have your work nodes which are
linux or windows and you can mix and
match these in a cluster so you can run
linux and windows
applications side by side in the same
kubernetes cluster should you want to
or need to but those worker nodes all
talk back to the control plane
reporting the status of the applications
that they're running
so generally speaking you'd want a
highly available control plane
probably three or five nodes and
disperse those across different
availability zones or regions in your
data centers or your cloud
you know just so that if one of your
regions or data centers goes down you
don't lose the whole thing
and that's the usual odd number odd
number isn't it it's usually
three five or seven yeah three five
sometimes
seven just to avoid split brain
scenarios and
if you're interested it's because i mean
there's more than this but um it runs
the raft consensus algorithm in the
background
for the preference yeah we've done a
show on raft and some other versions of
raft
earlier this year so i'll link to those
but they're yeah if you want to drill
down they're really good
and then i'd say as well you want to
deploy your working nodes across
different infrastructure zones as well
just because of course
as important as kubernetes and the
brains of the cluster are look the real
meat of everything is your business
applications
so you want those spread across
infrastructure as well and i would say
that that's like yet maybe a 50 000
view of kubernetes it's about masters
it's about nodes
but then when you come to applications
and i don't want to steal
some of your other questions potentially
but it's things like declarative
manifests and
desired state versus actual state or
observed state and things like that
that's perfect and when you talk about
the threes and the fives of masters and
workers
and then your different let's call them
availability nodes
would you have a three masters in each
availability node so
you split one in each yeah so generally
speaking
let's say you are running a data center
or a cloud
setup where you've got two availability
zones just to keep it simple yeah
yeah say like europe and us or something
yes yeah or even two areas within europe
or within the us
yeah doesn't really matter i would say
if you go with three
masters put two in one and one in the
other or if you go with five
five masters three in one zone and two
in the other zone
okay so you don't need the quorum yeah
so
as long as it can achieve quorum let's
say you've got those two availability
zones and you've got
two masters in one and one master in the
other and the network connectivity
between the two
goes down now both sides now
zone one we'll call it in zone two knew
that there used to be three masters
zone one can only see two and zone two
can only see one what
i picked the wrong numbers there didn't
i anyway one side can see two once i can
see one
they both knew they used to be three
well the side that can see two
knows that it has a majority so it can
form what we call a quorum
the other side knows that it doesn't
have a majority so it will effectively
put itself into read-only mode
the applications in that zone will still
run
but you can't perform updates against
them because that zone
knows that it doesn't have the majority
of nodes
it doesn't know whether the other two
are up or not so it says i'm going to be
careful i'm not going to write any
updates to the cluster config or to our
applications
just in case those other two are still
running and they're writing updates as
well
right so we've got masters that holds
all the
information and workers that do the the
work
so we've done masters and nodes what is
a declarative model
okay and this is a good one i think
because
at least for me right and i know it is
for other people
it can be a really hard one to wrap your
head around especially if it's super new
to you
so the idea of a declarative model
is to say to the platform and for us
that's kubernetes
you say what you want and you let
kubernetes do the hard work
so we might say we have an application
and it's got and we'll go dead simple
right because we haven't got diagrams to
help us here
it has a front end and a back end and i
want
five instances of the web front end
running and i want two instances
of a data store on the back end to keep
it highly available
that is what i want kubernetes and you
put a little bit more in there don't get
me wrong you say
the web front end should be based on
this container image and the data store
back end should be based on this
container image but i want five of the
front end
two of the back end you put that in a
yamaha file for kubernetes
and you post it to kubernetes an http
post yeah because it's all api driven
kubernetes looks at it and says right
i'm supposed to have five front end and
two back end at the moment when i
observe the cluster
i've got zero on the front end zero on
the back end of this config
so i'll go and do the hard work of
building five front end web servers
and two back end data stores in a high
availability formation
so kubernetes goes away and it does all
the hard work of pulling down container
images
starting containers joining them to
networks allocating network ports
kubernetes does all of that for you
because we've just said no manifest
you know i want five web front end
servers you tell them what port you want
it on and
what image and then kubernetes gets
those up and running
and it stores that in the cluster store
as its desired state this
is what we want and then it kind of sits
back puts its feet up
and it watches the cluster in the
applications and it's kind of polling at
all the time let's just call it polling
it it's not quite but
and it says it's checking the cluster
i've got five on the front two on the
back
happy days five on the front two on the
back happy days
then let's say something happens and we
lose a worker node
and let's just say to keep it easy we
have lost
two instances of the web front end so
kubernetes looks at the cluster i'm
supposed to have five
whoa hang on i've got three
it's you know general quarters all hands
to battle stations
we're supposed to have five we've got
three we need to spin another two up
so it spins another two up and brings it
back to that desired state of five
and it does all the clever stuff of
making sure you know as long as you've
got it configured properly
you know that it doesn't stick those two
new instances on the same node that's
already running another two if it's got
a node that's running on in a different
availability zone it will
you know can be clever enough to go and
spread them out like that so that's the
declarative state you don't
put together massive scripts that say
run this command to pull an image
run this command to start the container
run this command to expose it on this
port
none of that you just say to kubernetes
i want this
go and make it happen and by the way if
the state changes and i haven't told you
to change it
you do whatever hard work is required to
get it back to what i've asked for
and that's the model so my model is
what i want the application to be so let
me give you a quick
example right so let's say you're
building an extension on your house
and you contract a builder to do it it's
unlikely
and i mean some people might but it's
unlikely that you're gonna say
right in this extension i want the
foundations to be
three feet deep or whatever with this
type of cement and then i want 17
courses of bricks with
you know whatever insulation you have
you generally don't do that you will go
with a more high level plan and say look
i want an extension with three walls on
the back wall i want
a big window facing the garden and
i would like an oven that's got five
hobbs or whatever
it doesn't matter you don't go into the
detail telling the builder how to do the
work you just say
look this is almost a picture of the
kitchen extension that i want
go and build it and make sure it
conforms to that instead of you giving
the builder a massive long list of
saying
go to this tradesman and get this type
of brick go and get this type of ins
you don't you just say effectively to
kubernetes here's a picture of what i'm
after
make it happen make it so yeah so it's
not quite a blueprint it's just a
level above that it is a level above
that now don't get me wrong
we do go into a bit of detail like we
tell exactly which images to use and
which ports to use and things like that
but it is such a difference from like
i think the key is that when things
break here's an example when things
break
kubernetes knows what it's supposed to
have so it goes and does the work
to fix it back to that whereas if you
don't take a model like this and you've
built it with scripts
you're then logging on and you're
manually firing up two new instances
and you're choosing which nodes to put
them on and you're working out which
scripts to run
there's none of that you tell kubernetes
what to do if it breaks in the middle of
the night you sleep through it and you
wake up in the morning and you're like
cheers kubernetes for fixing it for me
cool so the desired state
is what the masters are trying to figure
out what constantly trying to work
towards that desired state yeah
and is that our desired state how we
want it to be or how
kubernetes wants it that's us so we say
we're kind of in charge we say we want
five web front ends and two database
back ends that's my desired state
kubernetes
and store that in the cluster store is
effectively a record of intent that's
what i want
and then kubernetes is constantly
observing the cluster making sure that
what it observes
matches what we've asked for matches our
desired state
so my model there is i want a web server
and a back end this is what they're made
up of
and the desired state is how many are
one and what they should look like
when they're live and up yeah absolutely
and these are all in yamo so yeah
another markup language
how do you test and verify that that
works the the yammer you've got yeah
don't don't get me wrong i mean
i do love yaml now but it
this was a question from one of the
other hosts that
has obviously got something going on at
the moment he's like oh can you make
sure you ask
how you test the ammo and verify it so
kubernetes does have it does let you do
dry runs of configs that you want
of your desired states that you're
wanting to push to the cluster
and we'll like we'll show you you know
what would happen if you were to apply
it
it will feed back to if you know you've
got the ammo syntax and stuff wrong
there are tools out there that will help
you with that as well
i'm actually not an expert on what those
tools are i'm not an expert on yaml
but i do absolutely love it these days i
used to hate it
but i think once you wrap your head
around it then it's actually quite a
friendly language in my opinion i
much prefer it over full-on json
yeah it's good just to have something
that everybody uses you know so you
don't have to think too much and i think
that's what
yeah goes to you know what i love about
it as well right
is that because we're defining our
applications in this yaml file or yaml
files
we're almost forced into a self
documentation like we're documenting to
kubernetes what we want what the
application should look like
so it we've automatically got a document
that let's just say
developers can give to operations you
know operations are always saying
document your apps tell us what their
compriser what do you need
well because we're forced to do that to
tell kubernetes to run it for us
we can also give that yaml file or those
yaml files to operations and say
this is our application and operations
can read it because the animal is not
hard to read
don't get me wrong you can get your
indentation wrong and i do all the time
but
you know just reading it as a human is
relatively easy it's easy to look at a
yaml file and say
okay got a web front end service here
based on
nginx version whatever and we're asking
for five replicas of it oh look it's on
port 8080
and we're pulling it from this
particular container registry
operations can easily look at that as
well you can onboard a new team member
and say
you know go and start working on this
application oh well what's the
application comprised of
read the yaml file and in that way it's
like a super powerful tool i think for
one of those more less technical jobs
you can on board people you can
talk to operations say look here's the
config of our app
yeah that's very true one question i
didn't ask when we were talking about
desired state is when the masters are
trying to get things
into that shape what would
in your experience be some of the
reasons that maybe one of the server web
servers just disappears
would that be your applications done
wrong or the hardware goes or
yes i mean i guess that's a common thing
yeah so you can have hardware failures
of the infrastructure like the server or
whatever that's hosting the virtual
machines or whatever
you can have network related issues and
i'm fond of blaming the network
i always used to do that in my previous
jobs the kubernetes agent
cubelet that runs on each working node
could also have crashed for whatever
reason i guess
any reason could cause any of your
worker nodes
to become unavailable there's also the
other thing as well though when you're
trying to deploy or to scale an
application
if you're doing it the right way and the
right way
is to say every time you deploy an
application or a
microservice you tell kubernetes what
its resource requirements are
you know so the minimum in order for it
to run and what its limits should be so
capping it from taking over the whole
system
if you're doing that with all of your
applications and your cluster gets full
and you say deploy a new instance of an
application or a new application or
or you manually try to scale part of an
application
up and it's it's demanding or it
requires more resources
than your worker nodes have available
then you will start to see parts of your
application go into the pending queue
so i don't think kubernetes does
anything special here or
i don't think it introduces any new
types of faults or problems
but those are generally the types of
things you will find from an
infrastructure and an application
perspective
perfect thank you two last bits in this
section before we move on to
example application we've managed to not
mention
pods or sidecars up into this point and
that would tie into my
last one which would be what is a
deployment so i think those three are
probably best
discussing together yeah that's rock and
roll on them yeah go for it so can you
take us through what a pod is
yeah side car and i suppose a deployment
would be
deploying our intended application to
kubernetes
yeah so i'll just wind it back a little
bit right so you take application code
just written in your your favorite
language or whatever and any of its
dependencies just like you would for if
you were to point to virtual machines or
whatever
its application source code and its
dependencies
you package those two together your app
code and dependencies
into a container or a container image
now docker runs containers natively on
its own platform okay
however kubernetes does not let you run
a container directly on kubernetes even
though
and this can be confusing even though
kubernetes is an orchestrator of
containerized applications
you can't run a container directly on
kubernetes in order to run that
it has to be wrapped in a pod so
it's it's quite often easy just to think
of a pod in a container as being the
same thing
the real difference is that a pod is
just a very thin
wrapper around the container that has a
bunch of metadata that kubernetes uses
so like you write your application and
you package it as a container
but like i just said kubernetes really
likes you to be able to say
well what resources does this container
require and what resources
should i cap it at on the node and
that's what you put inside the pod that
sort of wraps around the container
so kubernetes it's got high moral
standards it does not allow
nad containers to run on it you must
dress your containers in a pod
but it's such a super like thin
lightweight wrapper
now there are instances as you become
more advanced where you will deploy an
application
but that application needs a helper look
at let's just use let's use a service
mesh as an example okay let's say you're
deploying an application as a container
but you want to be able to extract
telemetry and let's say you want to
automatically encrypt traffic
that goes into that container and comes
out of it
kubernetes has a very powerful model
called the sidecar model
and they're different types of side cars
but we'll keep it pretty high level
um a service mesh which is a buzzword
these days but what allows
you to inject another container
into your application that then in the
service mesh model
sits between your main application and
the network
and intercepts all traffic coming into
your application and traffic that goes
out to it
allowing you to get great network
telemetry and things like that
but also enabling you without touching
your application code
to say i'm going to force traffic in and
out of this
application to be encrypted and you can
do that because the sidecar
is in between the application and the
network so the sidecar says
i'm encrypting everything and your
application doesn't even have to know so
you can
in a service mesh model you can take an
existing application that you've got
and not have to touch that application
code and be able to add network
telemetry
and mutual tls for authentication and
encryption
without having to touch your app because
you just throw the the service mesh side
car
into your application and it does it all
transparently for you
now gavin tell me if you don't think
that was well explained and we can go at
it again
no that's perfect that allows you well
in my head
to add new things to a pod
that's got a container within it you
know
different versions of it i always
understood
i think it was from your book that the
main thing you'd use it for is to go and
fetch some new information that
you might need to update something
that's shipped with the container you
know that was one of the examples
that's maybe a better example right more
of a simple example you might be running
a static web server that you've built as
a container
okay but you update the content that web
server is serving
and every time you make an update to
that you don't want to repackage and
retest and redeploy your container
so you would just run that web server
container have a sidecar container
alongside it that says i am periodically
pulling new content from github or from
a file server wherever
and i pull it to the local file system
that that con that the web container
is serving its content from so like your
own sort of
mini content distribution network cdn or
cache yeah why not
yeah that works yeah cool so what would
our container choices be
it doesn't just use docker does it
kubernetes it can use
anything that's oci that's right
yeah so in the early days kubernetes
heavily relied on docker to do all of
the low-level container functions like
pull container images start containers
join them to networks things like that
but people want twice so kubernetes now
has a
plugable container runtime layer called
the cri the container runtime interface
which basically says you can swap out
pretty much any container runtime that
you want
to do your low level pulling images and
starting and stopping containers
now kubernetes has just announced that
it will not be supporting full fat
docker going forward
yeah i saw that tweet last week yeah
it's created a bit of a storm
it's a storm in a teacup or it isn't
really a storm so we've been moving
towards this for a long time because
docker actually i'll call it full fat
docker full fat docker does
yes it pulls images and starts and stops
containers and all that stuff
but it does a whole bunch more and a
bunch more that kubernetes doesn't need
it to do
so kubernetes has always been moving
towards
a more cut down version of container
runtimes
that just do what kubernetes wants it to
do so for a long time now kubernetes has
used something called container d
which is actually a docker technology
donated
to i think the cncf and
kubernetes has and allowed you to run
container d instead of docker
for ages now just doing those low-level
functions
and a lot of people have been using
container d instead of docker for
kubernetes and
it just works but but look the point is
right
you can switch and swap which container
runtime is your favorite
and the reason or one of the reasons you
might want to do that is that
out of the box docker or container d
containers
are not as secure as virtual machines
they share the same host
kernel it's much easier to escape the
container and get access to the host
than it is from a virtual machine so
there are
other low-level container runtimes out
there that have a different workload
isolation model
to docker and container d and you might
need that for certain applications or
for certain
business units so the ability to say
for actually running my containers dock
is not a good fit for me or containers
not a good fit for me
maybe i don't know cutter containers or
g-visor one of the others
is a better fit for this application oh
i can easily swap it out
yeah as long as it's oci compliant
absolutely yes
so just to draw a line under the docker
depreciation for anyone that's familiar
with it it's a
depreciation of the shim isn't it that i
believe it is
yes yeah so it doesn't matter for most
developers really
i would say i mean of course always
do your testing especially if you're
running in production
but it is almost such low level plumbing
that
most of us don't even need to know
don't get me wrong business important
business applications i
i would never recommend saying you don't
need to know
but it's the kind of thing that most
people won't even
know has happened great so in relation
to pods and side cars what is a
deployment
so a deployment is a higher level object
that then wraps around a pod remember a
pod wraps around a container
and the reason for that is the pod will
add metadata that kubernetes uses maybe
for scheduling and resource requirements
and things
well then wrapping around a pod is a
deployment object
that brings things like the self healing
and the scalability
so the deployment object is where you
say i want 10 instances of this
always to be running getting back to our
desired state that we talked about
before
and it's a a place where you can say
i want to update the version of the
image that's being used
and the deployment will allow you to do
that as a buzzwords here i do apologize
but as a zero downtime rolling update so
like let's say you've got 10 instances
running or 10 containers or 10 pods
and we'll update one at a time we'll
wait five minutes in between each update
we'll run some tests in between
the deployment object has all of the
logic for that
so i like to think that that's where the
magic happens generally speaking you
will always be deploying
via a higher level object like a
deployment
now i'll say one thing a deployment
object
is the right way to deploy stateless
microservices
if your microservices are creating and
managing state or persisting data
then you will want to use a different
object maybe like a stateful set or
something
but the point is it's higher level than
a pod and it brings magic to the game of
self healing and updates and rollbacks
and things
so you'd find the desired state within
that deployment object correct
yes and the declarative model is just
the name for the thing
but yeah declarative model is just a
buzz word
for that ability to say i want five of
this make it
should make sure that it's always
looking like the desired state we could
actually look inside the deployment
config and see that okay let's quickly
summarize that
and stop me if i'm wrong the main
components of kubernetes are masters and
nodes
worker nodes there's an oci spec to help
people pick containers that would run
containers do not run on kubernetes
there they live inside a pod
which is basically like you go into your
it department
and say my phone's not working and they
need some more
context so the pod gives you context
the sidecar helps you build on things or
refresh things
are within that container that lives
inside the pod
and the desired state is really what we
want everything to be when it's live
which is contained with inside the
deployment
object but there are other types of
objects depending on how you want that
desired state to be
yes yeah works for me excellent
so the last section i've just made up an
app
so i was going to ask you to give us an
example of an app that would run on
kubernetes and i think we've done
a bit of that with a web server and back
end
and that was actually my example too i
was going to ask to
be taken through a public facing api
written in golang so it's a nice binary
it serves and saves some json over https
and it has a bit of a trickier back end
which is a push
cresql rdbms backend so there's some
state in there
so my question would be how would this
be packaged which would relate
to a deployment object so that would be
my first question then my second would
be
how do we deal with the persistent state
of the database
you've got two distinct elements of your
application there the stateless front
end and the state full back end
the front end would be built from your
source code into a container wrapped as
a pod
and then wrapped into a deployment that
says
i want however many of it you've got a
bunch of metadata that will help
kubernetes pick the right and
availability zones and all that kind of
stuff
and you would push that deployment to
kubernetes and kubernetes will
store it as a record of intent in the
cluster store and deploy those let's
call it five instances of the web front
end
and then it will sit in a loop watching
the cluster making sure that it's always
got five yeah if something breaks
kubernetes fixes it
lovely the second component of your
application
is a staple component now what we maybe
weren't clear about before is that a
deployment object
only defines one pod or one application
micro service
so we've got we've got two micro
services here a web front end and a
database back end
they can't be defined inside the same
deployment object
because if we were to say i want five
instances of it
what do you get five instances of the
web front end bit or the the database
back end bit
so if you let's say you've got five
different application components
you would need five different deployment
objects or
four deployment objects and a staple set
object
each service in your application is
wrapped by its own higher level object
am i making sense there gavin yeah
because otherwise if you
if you put them both in the same
deployment you'd have an api
speaking to a database and they'd all
have different things they'd be serving
that wouldn't they
yes now you can define them both
both separate objects in the same yaml
file with three dashes between the
objects
but they are different objects even
though they're in the same yaml file
now then for your database back end it
depends what your database is and how
you deploy it
but that would be deployed via a high
level object as well
could be a deployment uh could be a
stateful set as well
and then you've you've effectively told
kubernetes what you want we'll just say
five of the front end and two of the
back end post those config files those
yaml files to kubernetes and kubernetes
deploys them and watches them
now within your applications
you need to have done the work to
configure them to talk to each other
so obviously the api gateway at the
front end
will be exposing itself on a port you've
got to code that into your application
and you've got to put it in your pod
spec as well so that kubernetes knows
which ports to expose it on
you will also need to tell it how to
talk to the database on the back end
what port is the database listening on
do i have
any credentials that i need to present
to the database
in order for me to be able to write to
it and read from it
now then the model here is that you
don't code that runtime config
into your application you define it as a
separate object
and the reason for doing this is instead
of coding all of that
into your web front end so that it knows
the ports to expose itself on the ports
to talk to the database back end on
and more importantly any secrets that
are required to talk to the database
you don't want that shipping with your
web server because you package that as a
container image
and you store it in a repository
somewhere now of course you can secure
these repositories that are back and all
that kind of stuff
but it's just not a good model to put
that kind of configuration data
into your production application i mean
what if you need to change the port or
what if you need to change a secret
you then have to repackage your entire
application run it through
dev and test when qa and all that kind
of stuff
and then redeploy it it's a bit of a
pain so what we do is we keep the
application as simple as we can
it's a web server it pulls some data it
exposes
some port and it talks to some database
on some portal back end with some
credentials
we put that config and those credentials
in kubernetes objects so generally
speaking
we would put the config of the port and
things maybe in a config map
object and any sensitive information
like passwords and usernames
into a secret object and then at run
time
as part of that yaml configuration we
mount those config maps and those
secrets
into the web server so that it knows how
to talk to the back end
now don't get me wrong this is so much
easier to explain when you've got
diagrams and things like that
and i'm trying to be now that's fine
nigel it fits nicely
we in show 409 this year
we did a whole show on the 12 factor app
which talks about
putting your secrets and things into the
environment and
then your containers can see that
environment so i think that fits nicely
with
the config bit there okay so
the real tricky bit here is to make sure
you map what ports need to be public how
your apps broken down
and really visualize how each bit speaks
to each other
yeah so i think like you do you kind of
develop your application just as you
normally would
but you just got to think that like that
12-factor application
mindset of like i don't store my config
or my secrets in the application
but you write your application in the
normal code that you're writing in your
favorite languages
using whatever the the standard
requirements
and dependencies are the only difference
is like you just use
different tools to package it as a
container and just store your config and
your secrets
as kubernetes config mapping secret
objects and then a little bit of yaml
to just bind them all together but i
mean don't get me wrong
like the first time you do that it is
going to be probably a bit head
exploding
moment but it's so simple once you've
done it
it does force you into a nice into the
right way to do things doesn't it
once you've done it you're unlikely to
want to go back and do it the other way
once we've done all this and we get it
on to kubernetes just to
refresh that bit we're posting a
physical file to the master nodes army
and then it goes nothing
that's stuff with like curl or whatever
gui you're using
normally you would use the cube ctrl
command line tool but it's all
um http restful api so
curl yeah use rather yeah that could be
built into whatever
source code tool you're using that does
yeah whatever
post that okay and i mentioned it would
be
an api with an https front end
would we do that in the binary and run
the
https there or would we put something in
front of kubernetes to do all this
or does that depend on your model i'm
going to say that depends on your model
and you can do
either okay and where does dns fit into
all this
and tls i mean s fits in
many different layers so obviously you
will need if it's coming from the
internet your connections are coming
externally from the internet you will
need to have
the correct dns records um out there in
public
but also within your kubernetes cluster
so kubernetes runs its own internal dns
service that it uses
for service discovery so in our example
we've got two services a web front end
and a back end
you are going to configure your web
front end to talk to that
database back end using a name we don't
ever use
ips that doesn't change with kubernetes
so you would
include that name in the config map
for your web front end but then how does
it get resolved
to the containers or pods that are
actually running
that database back end and kubernetes
has an object called a service object
that does automatics and dns
registration and
does all of the name lookups and things
like that for you so it is auto magic
as long as you've configured it properly
i like that auto magic
and is the tls like the mutual tns
automatically there between things or
does it only do what you tell it to do
so you have to think about
you know it does what you want to do and
within your application and stuff
generally speaking the preferred model
is the service mesh model these days
it allows you to inject those side cars
that we talked about before
that will sit between your application
and the network and will automatically
do
the mtls for you without you having to
touch your application
so it makes it much easier because it's
just off the shelf now don't get me
wrong
service mesh requires an amount of
knowledge and expertise to deploy and
manage itself but that is again it is
the right
model instead of you touching your
application code
and having your developer of whatever
service have to
fudge some tls stuff into their code
that they're not necessarily wanting to
or very good at
bad model let's decouple the
mtls service let's call it from your
application
and just have it as a commodity that you
can just throw into your
your infrastructure perfect
and just to touch on persistent state
again so say we've
deployed it with cube control like
q-u-b-e
ctl command line tool masters are
figuring out what to do
we've got the five front end go along
api bits
and we've gone for a three node pro sql
setup
now the data that actually gets right
into the database and lives on the
what would in a virtual machine or
physical server on the hard
disks what do we decide
about that you know how do we make sure
that the next
version of postgresql spun up has access
to that data
gotcha okay so you would configure
postgres or whatever it is
and i'm not a postgres person but you
would configure that
into its own high availability formation
or configuration
and it would configure your web front
end to talk
to the live node or the master or
however it works the primary node yeah
and postgres will then take care of its
own
availability and things like that the
storage that
backs that increasingly going forward
you're going to use i'm just going to
call it external storage
now if you're on the cloud platform that
can be
google's persistent disks if you're on
gcp or it can be
elastic block storage if you're on aws
or it can be whatever their nfs is
because kubernetes now has the ability
for external storage
systems and look that can be netapp and
your headwigs and your emc's and things
or it can be your cloud zone storage
and have that exposed into kubernetes
just like you would expose external
storage area network san or nas storage
into virtual machines in the past so
that it's like
it's decoupled from your server
infrastructure
meaning that no matter which node you
spin an instance up on that external
storage can be connected into that node
so there's another abstraction layer
that you can just
document in the yaml and and it'll take
care of it
do you know what abstraction is like one
of the key words of modern applications
and modern infrastructure going forward
so kubernetes has a model now called the
container storage interface the csi
which allows you to take external
storage systems have their the life
cycle of the volumes that they create be
managed
and independently of your applications
and have
that's those storage resources connected
up to any application running on any
node in your cluster
dead easy and that just helps you grow
nicely as well because
as your things change you might need to
redeploy stuff in the traditional world
and you're like okay we're gonna have to
get a new
storage detached network all this type
of stuff but because it's abstracted on
this it makes it
easy just to not worry about that right
now okay and we're getting close to the
end
is there anything you want to mention
about the network requirements for
kubernetes
yeah so i'll take two things right so
from a network perspective right
when you deploy kubernetes for the most
part you will create a pod network
on your kubernetes cluster and it's a
vxlan
based overlay network that is extended
across
all kubernetes nodes in the cluster and
by default
it is wide open right so any application
you deploy to kubernetes goes on this
pod network and it's a free-for-all
they can all talk to each other which is
great well
i mean it makes life easy right yeah and
a vx lan is a virtual
line like if you imagine it being a
physical switch
you've got 48 ports on anyone that plugs
into that switch can
listen to all the traffic because it's
broadcasting around so you really want
to put
some segregation between each port yeah
so it lets you take
hosts and nodes that might be on
different physical underlay networks
and it lets you create a virtual network
like it tunnels through those
but it you're right it gives you
effectively a wide open network that all
of your applications can talk to
so you want to start then looking at
network policies to start saying we're
going to start locking things down a bit
because
while a wide open network is great when
you're developing and testing
you know it's one less hurdle to jump
over when you're building something to
play with
actually in production it's not what you
want so you need to start
securing things and network policies is
a great place to start
the other thing from a security
perspective i want to talk about and
it's not mtls related
but it's the fact that pods or
containers you might be running 50
on a node they all share that nodes
operating system kernel
so if one of them is compromised
and gets access to the hosts kernel
then all 50 containers on that node are
at risk
and that's scary stuff in production
right so
i just want people to be aware and this
is a little bit advanced okay
but as you're starting to deploy to
production you need to be looking at
some of the other technologies that
kubernetes supports
to start securing access to your hosts
kernel
and there are things like app armor and
se linux if you know ubuntu and red hat
linux okay
you can also do capability dropping so
drop
the capabilities of the root user in
your containers so that they don't have
full root access to your container
then you can also filter the syscalls
were a bit low level here
and but the requests that the
application in your container
can make to the hosts kernel and once
you start locking stuff like this down
then it can be super secure there's just
an amount of work
and an amount of testing that you must
be prepared to do
in order to really fully secure
something in production
yeah so you can go as deep as as you
need to there really
all right i'll need to wrap those up now
nigel
we could do another couple of hours i'm
sure we did a nice show
robert the show editor did a nice show
with rob
skellington skellington on high
cardinality and alerting and monitoring
obviously you've got the bit that you
want to monitor your app and that's
healthy and everything would i be right
in saying the key bits to monitor on
kubernetes would be the masters and the
nodes
or is there something off the shelf we
can look out for that yeah
no that so you you'd definitely want to
be monitoring your cluster i would just
refer to that as infrastructure that's
your managers and you know okay
and you want you know of course things
that will monitor your applications that
have application intelligence in there
security and monitoring are the two
least interesting topics in the world
for me
so i'm not an expert at them but i will
say that prometheus is a great tool to
start with
i'm not a prometheus expert but it's a
cncf project
it's massively used in the kubernetes
ecosystem
so you get all of like the the fact that
it's a well-developed
project that it's being constantly
worked on that it's been constantly
expanded what it can do
so in the world of monitoring prometheus
is a great place to start
perfect thank you yeah we've done a show
on prometheus so i'll get that
in the links so i'm going to wrap up now
obviously kubernetes is a very flexible
beast
but it doesn't have to be too scary if
there was one thing
a software engine engineer should
remember from our show what would you
like that to be
the kubernetes for all intents and
purposes looks like it is
nailed on as the future of
infrastructure for anything that
wants to be cloud native or running in
the cloud but just
if it's too complex for you and too much
to bite off
take a look at docker swarm okay that'll
be a good idea for another show actually
perfect was there anything we missed
that you would have liked me to mention
or thought should it be mentioned
i don't think so i mean like you say we
could go
all day all day yeah i mean the title is
kubernetes fundamentals i think
we've done a good job yeah i think
that's it uh where can people find more
about you you've got your twitter
account but you know what's the best way
to reach out
i'm pretty much at nigel poulton
everywhere twitter github linkedin
i'm more than happy to engage with
people i mean i can't be free technical
support for hard questions
because i'm super busy but i i you know
i make a living out of helping
make kubernetes easier for people so by
all means please reach out at nigel
poulton
all my stuff my books my video training
courses
to book me for a company live stream and
things like that just go to
nigelpolton.com
i'm going to finish right by saying it's
not hubris that
i'm nigel potent.com or anything like
that it's just i used to be
a windows guy and then i was a linux guy
and then i was a storage guy and i've
been a network guy now i'm a containers
guy
i don't want to be like kubernetes nigel
somewhere because
like in five years time i might i might
be something different
so i just keep it easy i just go with my
name everywhere that i
am i've done anything so what you're
saying kubernetes isn't going to be here
in five years
no that's rude it will be what i'm
saying is
me as an individual i'm a techaholic
right
and the best thing about technology for
me is the mystery of it and i love
learning things
so once kubernetes becomes super stable
and no longer of interest to me then
i'll be on to the next
interesting groundbreaking yeah i get
you
perfect well nigel thank you for coming
on the show it's been a real pleasure
this is gavin henry for software
engineering radio
thank you for listening thanks for
listening to sc radio an educational
program brought to you by ieee software
magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening